

Mobile1: +91 7501552243

Mobile2: +91 9434365243

Soumadip Biswas

SUMMARY

6+ years of academic research experience and 10+ years of cumulative programming experience in industry and academia. Eager interest in developing as well as learning new methods for solving problems and improving existing solutions. Demonstrated capability of identifying and solving problems through research and analysis. Looking for opportunities that require exploration of new network technologies such as 5G, NFV, SDN, and in computer systems such as distributed systems, operating system, etc.

CONTACT Information

Gen. Research Lab, Dept. of CSE IIT Kharagpur

India - 721302 Email1: soumadip.b@iitkgp.ac.in Website: soumadip.github.io. Email2: soumadip.cse@gmail.com Orchid id: 0000-0002-6838-7657 LinkedIn: in/soumadipbiswas

EDUCATION

Indian Institute of Technology Kharagpur, Kharagpur, India.

Ph.D. (Thesis Submitted), Dept. of Computer Science & Engineering 2014—22.

• Advisors: Dr. Arobinda Gupta and Dr. Sandip Chakraborty

M.Tech., School of Information Technology 2010—12

• Advisor: Dr. Soumya K. Ghosh

West Bengal University of Technology, Kolkata, India.

B.Tech., Computer Science & Engineering

2006—10

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Associate Professor, Institute of Engineering and Management. 2022—present Courses taught: Data Structures and Algorithms (Theory and Lab), Formal Languages and Automata Theory.

Guest Faculty, Indian Association for the Cultivation of Science. Autumn 2022

Course taught: Introduction to Computing with Python.

Industry Experience

Software Engineer, Citrix R & D India Pvt. Ltd.

2012-2014

I worked as a developer for an application virtualization tool called XenApp using C#, C++. I was responsible for fixing problems faced in deployed products by providing feature enhancements and bug fixes.

During this time, I have gained experience in i) remote and local debugging, ii) distributed systems problems, iii) responsible coding, and iv) communications. Also, on some occasions, I had helped in achieving a multi-party consensus.

I received a promotion from Software Engineer 1 to Software Engineer 2 within 1 year of joining.

ACADEMIC EXPERIENCE

Research Scholar, Indian Institute of Technology Kharagpur. 2014—22

Algorithms for Handover Management in Dense LTE Networks under

Vehicular Mobility: Reduction in the number of handovers is desirable for providing
good quality of service. However in a densely deployed LTE network, for high-speed
users, achieving this has its own set of problems. In this regard, we have provided

some solutions published in reputed journals and conferences.

During this time, I have gained experience in i) identifying and modeling problems, ii) designing experiments through technical analysis and iii) open-source simulation tools.

Teaching Assistant: Algorithms, Distributed Systems, Parallel and Distributed Systems, Programming and Data Structures, Advanced Graph Theory, Performance Modeling of Computer Networks, Computational Complexity, Geospatial Information System, Internet and Web Technology.

Projects Mentored: Distributed Chat, Distributed logging, Collaborative Download, Cluster Middleware, Publish-Subscribe System, P2P System, Vector Clock, Distributed Clock Synchronization.

Masters Thesis, Indian Institute of Technology Kharagpur.

2011-12

Geospatial Services in Cloud Infrastructure: In this work, using only opensource tools, we successfully deployed a first-generation IaaS cloud. We further demonstrated that data-intensive geospatial services (e.g. WFS, WMS, WPS) can be safely deployed in a cloud environment by utilizing SaaS while respecting the privacy of multiple participating parties.

Bachelor Project, West Bengal University of Technology.

2009 - 10

Web-Enabled Cluster Computing with Customized Load Balancing: In this work, we provided a proof of concept that large computation can be remotely performed over commodity hardware and low-bandwidth connection by utilizing the Beowulf cluster and MPI.

RESEARCH INTERESTS

Advances in Computer and Cellular Networking, Graph Theory and Algorithms, Distributed Systems and Algorithms, and Operating Systems.

ACHIEVEMENTS

- Ph.D Scholarship awarded by MHRD, Govt. of India for 2014—19.
- M.Tech Scholarship awarded by MHRD, Govt. of India for 2010—12.
- All India Rank 330 (99.69th %ile) in GATE 2010.

SKILLS

Technical:

- Programming: Python, C, C++, Shell scripting, SQL.
- Framework: Network Simulator (NS3), LENA, SUMO.
- Database: MySQL.
- OS: Linux, Windows.

Communication:

- English (C2), Bengali (C2, Native).
- Hindi (C1).

Publications (Conference)

- S. Biswas, S. Chakraborty, and A. Gupta, "Reducing Spurious Handovers in Dense LTE Networks based on Signal Strength Look-ahead," IEEE International Conference on Wireless and Mobile Computing, Networking and Communications (WiMob) 2018, Limassol, Cyprus, 2018.
- S. Biswas, A. Gupta, and S. Chakraborty, "A Framework for eNB Load Balancing in Dense LTE Networks," IEEE International Symposium on Personal, Indoor and Mobile Radio Communications (PIMRC) 2019, Istanbul, Turkey, 2019.

Publications (Journal)

 S. Biswas, A. Gupta, and S. Chakraborty, "Load-balanced User Associations in Dense LTE Networks", Computer Networks, Vol. 189, 2021.

Publications (Other)

 S. Biswas, S. Chakraborty, and A. Gupta, "Poster Abstract: Balanced User Association in Dense LTE Networks," IEEE International Conference on Computer Communications (INFOCOM) 2019, Paris, France, 2018.

References

Arobinda Gupta, Professor Dept. of Computer Science & Engineering Indian Institute of Technology Kharagpur

Sandip Chakraborty, Associate Professor Dept. of Computer Science & Engineering Indian Institute of Technology Kharagpur

Soumya K. Ghosh, Professor Dept. of Computer Science & Engineering Indian Institute of Technology Kharagpur E-mail: agupta@cse.iitkgp.ac.in Phone: +91 - 3222 - 283476

E-mail: sandipc@cse.iitkgp.ac.in Phone: +91 - 3222 - 282898

> E-mail: skg@iitkgp.ac.inPhone: +91 - 3222 - 282332